Guida West Papers, 1946-2006
Sophia Smith Collection
Guida West papers
1946-2006
West, Guida
MS 555
51.25 linear ft.
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Political sociologist; activist; author. The papers focus primarily on West's activism, research, professional activities, speeches, and writings related to welfare rights and economic justice. Her extensive working files document individuals and organizations working for civil rights, welfare rights, and related social movements from the 1960s to the early 2000s. Organizations represented include the Montclair Welfare Rights and Friends of Welfare Rights, National Welfare Rights Organization (NWRO), New Jersey Friends of Welfare Rights, the United Church of Christ's Welfare Priority Team, the United Presbyterian Church, Synod of New Jersey, Committee on Church and Society and Commission on Religion and Race (SynCORR), the Women's Committee of One Hundred, and the Welfare Made a Difference National Campaign (WMAD). Extensive files on leaders in the welfare rights movement include tape recorded and transcribed interviews done in the mid-1970s and mid-1980s.
Margarida "Guida" Pyles and her twin sister Yolanda Thereza were born November 9, 1927 in Sao Paulo, Brazil to Richard Milton and Etelvina Pacheco e Silva Pyles. Richard M. Pyles, an electrical engineer, descended from an Irish immigrant who emigrated from Mississippi to Americana, Brazil after the U.S. Civil War. Guida was graduated from Escola Graduada in 1944 and Colegio MacKenzie in Sao Paulo in 1945, then went to work as a bilingual secretary for General Motors de Brasil.
Finding that American institutions were eager for foreign students, Pyles applied and was accepted at sixteen U.S. colleges. She chose to attend Barnard College beginning in the fall of 1946 and completed an AB in mathematics in 1950. Unable to find a job in mathematics, she went to work in September 1950 as an executive bilingual secretary at the Brazilian Mission to the United Nations. When Hugo Gouthier, her boss at the U.N., changed jobs, she continued as his private secretary from 1953 until the Fall of 1958 while also pursuing graduate study in sociology at Columbia University. An important influence on her later work was a seminar with Paul Lazarsfeld concerning the impact of McCarthyism on racism in southern schools. She completed her M.A. in 1959.
Guida Pyles married John Maurice West, a chemical engineer, on February 3, 1951. After she suffered several miscarriages, the Wests adopted a daughter, Laura, in the spring of 1960. West later gave birth to a son, Paul.
Though a contemporary curriculum vita lists her occupation as "fulltime caregiver to two children" for the years 1960-70, West became intensely involved in the civil rights and welfare rights movements during these years. West described her motivation in an interview:
"I suppose for me it began as a young child in Brazil. We had a servant who was the son of a slave. He had almost no opportunity for formal schooling, but he was a brilliant man. As I grew older, and my respect for his ability increased, it seemed a terrible thing to me that this sickness in our society could cause us to lose the talent of such a man." (from "Local Brotherhood Award Winner Is a 'Do-Gooder' In the Best Sense," by Louise Saul, The Recorder, Metuchen, NJ, 17 Feb 1966)
Some of her earliest efforts were related to fair housing, developing a "Covenant of Open Occupancy" for Metuchen. She was also a charter member and "pioneer" of the Metuchen-Edison Racial Relations Council, which awarded her its first Brotherhood Award in 1966. She also served on the Montclair Council for Community Action, Essex County Legal Services, the Task Force to Support the Kilmer Job Corps, and the Montclair Interracial Council.
In a speech to the local NAACP in 1966, West recalled the day she became a U.S. citizen in 1961: "…that morning--as a new American--it was difficult for me to repeat the last six words of the pledge-'with liberty and justice for all.' For in our group there stood persons of minority groups to whom I knew liberty and justice are in reality just beautiful words and part of the unfulfilled American dream."
Convinced that the struggle for human rights, which she called "the struggle of our generation," must begin in the church, West organized a Church and Society Committee in her own parish, the First Presbyterian Church in Metuchen in 1961. "As a Presbyterian, I was told to comfort the afflicted and afflict the comfortable," she explained in a 1999 speech. This work led to her appointment in 1965 to the Commission on Religion and Race of the Presbyterian Synod of New Jersey (SynCORR).
When the Wests moved in 1966, they tested the town's new "Covenant of Open Occupancy" and sold their house to an African-American family. This resulted in a "campaign of harassment" that included angry phone calls, and letters, a rift with John's parents, and the posting of a lawn sign saying, "Nigger Lovers, Niggers, Block-Busters Keep Out."
In the spring of 1967 West and Nel Van Dijk, both members of the Presbyterian Synod of New Jersey's Church and Society Committee, indicated that they would like to see the Committee address "the new welfare reform." The Committee responded by asking the two women to prepare a report on the issue. "Still No Room at the Inn: A Report on Public Assistance," completed in October of 1967, provided the basis of West's life's work. Though she began with "all the stereotypes" about people on public assistance, West later said she was "transformed by the study." The "immorality of the existence of poverty in such an affluent society as ours" turned her from a "do gooder" to understanding the issue as a matter of "self interest."
The summer 1967 riots in Newark added urgency to her work for racial and economic justice. As a Ford Foundation Urban Fellow, 1967-68, West served as chair and organizer for Seminars on the Urban Crisis for the Urban Training Institute of Essex County in 1969, The Right To Live Conference in 1969, the New Jersey Mobilization Against Hunger in 1971, and co-chair of the Public Welfare Seminar sponsored by the New Jersey Council of Churches in 1968.
As West's interest in welfare grew, she soon got involved in local welfare rights work, serving on Welfare Task Forces in her church, in Essex County, and for the Urban Training Institute. West helped to organize a New Jersey Friends of Welfare Rights Organization in Newark. The group met for the first time in February of 1970.
In a draft statement, possibly for a graduate school application, West wrote that involvement with civil rights and welfare rights as a volunteer prompted her to realize the inadequacy of her background "…even with my own personal continuous study." She wrote, "a volunteer does not carry the power or the influence that a professional does… I want to use my available working years the most efficiently and effectively possible." To that end, she entered a Ph.D. program in sociology at Rutgers University in the fall of 1970.
Fascinated by the unique structure, strategies, and goals of the welfare rights movement, West decided to make it the subject of her thesis research. The National Welfare Rights Organization (NWRO) worked to establish the concept of a minimum standard of living as a citizenship right and a human right, continuing and extending the civil rights movement's "right to live" concept to include economic justice. Welfare recipients could join local Welfare Rights Organizations (WRO) which were affiliated with state, regional, and the national group. Supporters could join Friends of Welfare Rights Organizations (FWRO) to provide financial and other support, but could not dictate policy or strategy. This "twin track" structure of WROs and FWROs became the focus of West's research.
West's decision to study the movement necessitated a change in role for her from that of "participant-observer" to "participant-observer" as of July 1971. She kept very detailed field notes; joined mailing lists; collected flyers, publications, and clippings; attended conferences and meetings; and interviewed more than fifty key participants in the welfare rights movement.
With the women's movement of the 1970s, West began to recognize obstacles she faced as a woman activist. Though she was driven by the principles of tolerance, caring, and responsibility ("my understanding of Christian principles") ingrained by her father, she realized that she had not been socialized for conflict or to be assertive. She found it personally difficult to let go of the traditional wife and mother role, and the work she chose resulted in the loss of friends, conflict with family members, and threats to her children. Yet, she explained, "the women I worked with became my sisters," like a new family, "I cared deeply what happened to them."
While working on her thesis, West served as consultant sociologist to the newly-established Welfare Priority Team of the United Church of Christ from 1971 until the NWRO disbanded in 1974.
West earned a Ph.D. in sociology from Rutgers in 1978. Her thesis, "The National Welfare Rights Movement: Social Protest of Welfare Women (1966-1976)," became her first book, The National Welfare Rights Movement: The Social Protest of Poor Women, which was published by Praeger in 1981. West described her work as an exploration of the question, "How do you bring about change?"
In the author's preface, West reflects that the work taught her "a great deal about my own paternalistic behavior and attitudes as well as the institutional racism prevalent in our society."
In her "Commentary" for West's book, the NWRO's Johnnie Tillmon wrote: "Guida West's story of the National Welfare Rights movement tells it like it was and how it came to be…. It is important because it is the history of poor women - especially poor Black women and poor White women and poor Hispanic women - in the United States. This is a history that is not often, if ever written about. Anyone who cares to understand about being poor in this country will learn much about our struggle in these pages."
After completing her Ph.D., West held various posts at Rutgers University between 1974 and 1987, including Coordinator of Continuing Education for Women in the Extension Division (1974-80), Assistant Professor of Sociology (1978-87), and Special Projects Administrator in the Institute for Research on Women (1987-89). She developed and supervised The New Jersey Project on Inclusive Scholarship, Curriculum and Teaching (the first statewide, state-funded gender and multi-cultural scholarship and curriculum project in the U.S.), obtained grant funding to establish the Training Institute for Sex Desegregation of the Public Schools in 1975, and developed and implemented policy/action conferences on Displaced Homemakers and Adolescent Pregnancy prevention. She also helped to found the Rutgers Women's Center, the Rutgers Institute for Research on Women, the Rutgers Women's Studies Program, and the Begin Again (B.A.) Program for Women.
In 1983, West initiated a research project to study the "patterns of change in the political behavior and ideology" of a sample of national welfare rights leaders from their early years through the heyday of the welfare rights movement and into the early 1980s. The end result was intended to be a book, originally titled "Welfare Rights Leaders in a Becalmed Movement" and later, "Protest Leadership Outcomes: Welfare Rights Leaders a Decade Later." Though the book was never completed, West presented the research (including extensive interviews with NWRO leaders) in a number of conference papers beginning in 1984.
After being denied tenure at Rutgers, West went to work in 1989 as Director of Policy, Advocacy and Research for the Federation of Protestant Welfare Agencies, Inc. (FPWA). In this capacity she gave testimony, and represented FPWA on various committees and boards associated with welfare and economic justice.
West and Rhoda Lois Blumberg compiled an anthology of essays, Women and Social Protest, about women's involvement in social change. Published by Oxford University Press in 1990, the book included articles by sociologists, political scientists, historians, and experts in women's studies. West authored a chapter titled "Women in the Welfare Rights Movement."
Beginning in 1990 she co-founded and co-directed the Welfare Reform Network (WRN) of New York City "to mobilize advocates and clients to influence welfare and poverty issues." The early 1990s brought Republican "Contract With America" efforts to change welfare, combined with Bill Clinton's 1992 campaign pledge to "reform welfare as we know it." In 1995, as federal legislation began to take shape, West was instrumental in forming the Women's Committee of One Hundred (WC100), a coalition of welfare recipients, social welfare professionals, activists, poverty lawyers, and others. WC100, which saw the reform effort as an attack on women's sexual and economic autonomy, worked to influence public opinion and counteract the prevailing narrative about welfare.
After her retirement from FPWA in December of 1994, West continued as a consultant to FPWA on poverty, income security, and welfare reform. She remained an involved activist for economic justice until advancing age and failing eyesight curtailed her activities.
The Guida West Papers consist of 51.25 linear ft. dating from 1946 to 2006. Types of materials include correspondence, minutes, notes, photographs, press releases, reports, interviews, journal and newspaper articles, photographs, publications, speeches, writings, audiotapes, and memorabilia.
The bulk of the papers date from 1962 to 2006 and focus on West's activism, research, professional activities, speeches, and writings related to welfare rights and economic justice. Because the subject of West's research was the structure and strategies of local, regional, and national welfare rights organizations and their supporting Friends organizations, she assembled all of the documentation she could obtain, subscribed to many mailing lists, and kept very detailed notes on conversations, meetings, public events, and conferences. Her extensive working files are a treasure trove of information about individuals and organizations working for civil rights, welfare rights, and related social movements from the 1960s to the early 2000s.
Her notes on conversations and annotations on meeting minutes provide a behind-the-scenes "you were there" sense of events as they unfolded with after-the-fact analysis supplied by files related to her speeches and writings.
Files related to the Women's Committee of One Hundred (WC100) include candid personal communications and notes on the group's strategy sessions. Their communications provide a rare look into the strategic thinking and highly fraught debates these allies of poor women were engaged in, especially in their ongoing conflicts with conservative Republicans, a Democratic president and congress facing tough re-election campaigns, and with some white second-wave feminists who insisted that ending welfare supported feminist goals.
The papers contain only a minimal amount of personal information.
ACRONYMS:
AFDC = Aid to Families with Dependent Children
ARC = Applied Research Center
BHM = [United Church of Christ] Board for Homeland Ministries
BOB Coalition = Building Opportunities Bonus Coalition, NOW Legal Defense and Education Fund
CLASP = Center for Law and Social Policy
E&RJPT = Economic and Racial Justice Priority Team of the UCBFHM
EITC = Earned Income Tax Credit
FPWA = Federation of Protestant Welfare Agencies
FRAC = Food Research Action Center/Council
FWRO = Friends of Welfare Rights Organization
IFCO = Interreligious Foundation for Community Organization
IRW = Institute for Research on Women, Rutgers University
IWPR = Institute for Women's Policy Research
JOBS = Job Opportunity and Basic Skills Program
JSAC = Joint Strategy and Action Committee, Inc.
KWRU = Kensington Welfare Rights Union
MEJ = Movement for Economic Justice
MERRC = Metuchen-Edison Race Relations Council
MFWR = Montclair Friends of Welfare Rights
MMR = Montclair Mothers' Rights
NAHC = National Anti-Hunger Coalition
NCC = National Council of Churches
NCCP = National Center for Children in Poverty
NWRO = National Welfare Rights Organization
NWRU = National Welfare Rights Union
NWSA = National Women's Studies Association
REACH= Resources for Education to Assist Children (NJ)
SCAN = Social Concerns Action Network
SynCORR = Synod of New Jersey Commission on Religion and Race
TANF = Temporary Assistance for Needy Families
TISD = Training Institute for Sex Desegregation
TOP = Trenton Office Program, New Jersey Conference of Churches
UCBHM = United Church [of Christ] Board For Homeland Ministries
UCC = United Church of Christ
WISC = Washington Interreligious Staff Community
WMAD = Welfare Made a Difference National Campaign
WPT = Welfare Priority Team of the United Church of Christ
WRI = Welfare Rights Initiative
WRISC = Welfare Rights Information and Support Community
WRO = Welfare Rights Organization
WRN = Welfare Reform Network of New York City
This collection is organized into eleven series:
I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS (1946-2006, n.d.)
II. CORRESPONDENCE (1954-2005, n.d.)
III. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES (1954-2003, n.d.)
IV. CONFERENCES AND MEETINGS (1968-2004)
V. INDIVIDUALS (1966-2001, n.d.)
VI. ORGANIZATION FILES (1961-2006, n.d.)
VII. SPEECHES AND TESTIMONY (1965-2001, n.d.)
VIII. WRITINGS (1971-2000, n.d.)
IX. SUBJECT FILES (1971-2000, n.d.)
X. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS AND COMPUTER MEDIA (1971-2002, n.d.)
XI. ARTIFACTS ( 1968-95, n.d.)
OVERSIZE MATERIALS
The Papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions. Original audiovisual materials are closed--copies must be made for research use. Digital copies are available for most of the audiocassettes (see Appendix).
Guida West donated her Papers to the Sophia Smith Collection in 2006.
Afro-American women-History--20th century-Sources; Christianity and politics-Presbyterian Church-United States-History-20th century; Civil rights movements--United States--History--20th century-Sources; Displaced homemakers; Feminism--United States--History-Sources; National Welfare Rights Organization (U.S.); New Jersey Friends of Welfare Rights; Poor women--United States--History--Sources; Poverty--United States--History--Sources; Public welfare--United States--History--Sources; Race relations--United States--History--20th century-Sources; Social justice-History-20th century; Tillmon, Johnnie; United Church Board for Homeland Ministries. Race Relations Dept.; United Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A. Synod of New Jersey; Welfare Made A Difference National Campaign; Welfare rights movement-New Jersey; Welfare rights movement--United States--History--Sources; Welfare recipients--Employment--New Jersey--History-Sources; West, Guida; Women in the Presbyterian Church-United States--History; Women--Employment--United States--History-Sources; Women's Committee of One Hundred; Women's studies--History--Sources
APPENDIX: Digital Audio Files Made from Standard Audio Cassettes
These digital files are available for research use. Please consult the reference staff about access.
Filename: Title
wes_001: National Welfare Rights Organization Conference, 30 Jul 1971
wes_002: United Church of Christ, Welfare Priority Team meeting, 3 Feb 1972
wes_003: United Church of Christ [WPT mtg ?], 3 Feb 1972
wes_004: Welfare Rights Organization Meeting, Montclair, 7 Feb 1972
wes_005: Conf Health Session, 8 Mar 1972
wes_006a: United Church of Christ, Welfare Priority Team #3 side 2, 17 Mar 1972
wes_006b: Banquet Awards etc. "no good" side 10
wes_007a: United Church of Christ, Welfare Priority Team #1, side 6, 17 May 1972
wes_007b: United Church of Christ, Welfare Priority Team #2, Panel H&W Chicago side 5, 17 May 1972
wes_008a: United Church of Christ, Welfare Priority Team, #1, Welfare Rights, side 7, 17 May 1972
wes_008b: United Church of Christ, Welfare Priority Team, Shinn side 8, 17 May 1972
wes_009a: Welfare Council Planning Meeting 5/25/72 side 1, 25 May 1972
wes_009b: Welfare Council Planning Meeting 5/25/72 side 2
National Welfare Rights Organization, Conference, Miami Beach 1972
wes_010a: [#1]; A.M. session, G. Wiley and Church Caucus Bob O'Donnell leading," 6 Jul 1972
wes_010b: [#1]; Church Caucus, 6 Jul 1972
wes_011a: #2, 6 Jul 1972
wes_011b: #2, 6 Jul 1972
wes_012a: #3; Plenary, 7 Jul 1972
wes_012b: #3; Coalition Workshops, 7 Jul 1972
wes_013a: #4; Coalition(?), 7 Jul 1972
wes_013b: #4; Church Caucus II, 8 Jul 1972
wes_014a: #5; Church plenary, 8 Jul 1972
wes_014b: #5; CPSDT, Jul 1972
wes_015: George Wiley interviewed by Paul Sherry, "Always on Sunday " radio show, 15 Apr 1973
wes_016: NWRO Convention 1973 Friends Meeting, 1973
wes_017: Paul Sherry interview, United Church of Christ, 5 Jul 1974
wes_018: Robert Langer interview, Health and Welfare Council of Metropolitan St. Louis, 11 Jul 1974
wes_019: Tim Sampson interview, 12 Jul 1974
wes_020: Welfare Rights Information and Support Community, 1974
wes_021: "UCC WPT/WRISC St Louis [side B didn't record]" tape recording of television program, New York Illustrated, "Welcome to Welfare," narrated by Ruby Dee, 18 Oct
wes_022: WRISC Workshop [side B "practically empty"], 1974
National Welfare Rights Organization Conference, 1974
wes_023a: #2; Mayor St. Louis, Frankie Jeter, Beulah Sanders, Jul 1974
wes_023b: #2; Johnnie Tillmon, Jul 1974
wes_024a: #3; Morning plenary, National Caucus on Black Aged, 12 Jul 1974
wes_024b: #3; Gray Panthers, 12 Jul 1974
wes_025: #4; a.m. workshop, WRO Mothers Speak-Ethel Mae Matthews from Atlanta "Excellent," 12 Jul 1974
wes_026a: #6; Bert de Leeuw speech, 13 Jul 1974
wes_026b: #6; Plenary afternoon, 12 Jul 1974
wes_027: Bert de Leeuw tape #2 29 Jul 1974 [may have been taped over with "Helen W." [Webber] 1 Oct 1974, NYC [leftover bit of Bert de Leeuw starts at minute 40]
wes_028: Joe Merchant, WPT [taped over Bert de Leeuw] side B says "half tape didn't come out" 26 Sep 1974 at UCC
wes_029: Johnnie Tillmon, 30 Jul 1974
wes_030: Tape # 2 J. Tillmon 30 Jul 1974[may be taped over]/Hulbert James, 26 Sep 1974
wes_031: "Always on Sunday" radio show with Paul Sherry of UCC, Helen Webber, Beulah Sanders, Richard Cloward, a week after the death of George Wiley "very good on coalitions, HW, accomplish. of mov. MEJ rationale," 8 Aug 1973
wes_032a: Faith Evans of NWRO interview in NYC, 11 Sep 1974
wes_032b: Frances Fox Piven [Faith Evans crossed out], 13 Sep 1974
wes_033: March 4 Drugs &Abortion, side 13 and 14, 4 Mar
wes_034: Speech by Anne McGrew Bennett "Women in a New Society," undated
wes_035a: United Church of Christ group discussion re New York state abortion law, undated
wes_035b: United Church of Christ group discussion re New York state abortion law,undated
wes_036: Guida West, some views on legal services and the historical development of the Legal Services Corporation [side B blank, I think], 3 Mar 1979
wes_037: Madeline Adamson #1 [side B blank, I think], 30 Jan 1984
wes_038: Madeline Adamson 2nd part, Rafe Pomerance [side B blank, I think], 30 Jan 1984
wes_039: Bobbie Bennett, NWSA, 26 Jun 1984
wes_040: Barbara Brown, Camden, NJ, 4 Jun 1984
wes_041: Joyce Burson, Washington DC, 16 Jun 1984
wes_042: Catherine Dandridge cont'd &Rosie Lee, Chicago "very poor tape, erased 20 minutes by accident", 12 Apr 1984 [see also microcassette 126]
wes_043: Maud Davis tape #1, Larry Richardson on tape also, Newark, 16 Mar 1984
wes_044: Maud Davies tape #2, Larry Richardson on tape also, Newark, 16 Mar 1984
wes_045: Bert De Leeuw [says "copy" but we don't seem to have an original], 31 Jan 1984
wes_046: Ruby Duncan, Nevada, 29 Feb 1984
wes_047: Faith Evans [#1] "side #1 didn't come out," 18 Jan 1984